<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Chinese Poetry</title>
    <description>Translated by Steve Lipscombe.</description>
    <link>http://localhost:4000/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:4000/feed/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Sun, 12 Feb 2023 09:28:42 +0100</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 12 Feb 2023 09:28:42 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v4.3.1</generator>
    
      
    
      
        <item>
          
            <title>Writing On A Happening</title>
          
          <author> (Chinese Poetry)</author>
          <description>
            &lt;p&gt;The fifth translation in this endeavour, and our second poem by Wang Wei about the colour of moss&lt;!--more--&gt;. I discovered this poem a few weeks ago when reading through an anthology of Wang Wei’s works, and it has been lodged in the back of my mind ever since. It is a vivid and visual delight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;書事&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;輕陰閣小雨，&lt;br /&gt;
深院晝慵開。&lt;br /&gt;
坐看蒼苔色，&lt;br /&gt;
欲上人衣來。&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Writing On A Happening&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A faint shade stopped the drizzle &lt;br /&gt;
deep in courtyard daylight yet &lt;br /&gt;
too lazy to open the gate &lt;br /&gt;
I sat watching the green moss’ greenness &lt;br /&gt;
as if it were climbing my robe &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;translation-notes&quot;&gt;Translation notes&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The title of this poem is important, because it implies an event (or series of events) so notable had occurred that Wang Wei had to record it in detail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ge&lt;/em&gt; 閣 in the first line means to stop. It’s that the poem is being written from the subjective and imaginative perspective of the poet: the coming of shade doesn’t cause rain to stop, but as he perceived the scene, it did. It almost lends this faint shade a magical or supernatural power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second line is where this poem starts to reveal its character, and where I think two lines are required in English to convey the original one line in Chinese. &lt;em&gt;Shen&lt;/em&gt; 深 is usually translated as ‘deep’ - in &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/poets/wang-wei/deer-place&quot;&gt;Deer Place&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; this character was used to describe the ‘deep forest’. &lt;em&gt;Yuan&lt;/em&gt; 院 means ‘courtyard’, and &lt;em&gt;zhou&lt;/em&gt; 晝 is usually translated as ‘daytime’. So, one might be tempted to take these three characters at face value, and translate the beginning of the second line as ‘deep in the courtyard during daytime’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, &lt;em&gt;shen&lt;/em&gt; 深 is occasionally used to describe deep, vivid, saturated hues. If we remember the faintness of the shade alluded to in the line above, the challenge is to continue the theme of light and colour (this comes in useful later), while also getting across the time of day. Therefore, ‘deep in courtyard daylight’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The time of day is important because the next two characters don’t give us much. &lt;em&gt;Yong&lt;/em&gt; 慵 means lazy and &lt;em&gt;kai&lt;/em&gt; 開 means open. The gate to the courtyard is implied, and the laziness is further implied because it’s already daytime (as signified by &lt;em&gt;zhou&lt;/em&gt; 晝, mentioned above) and the gate is still closed. As well as being connected to the character &lt;em&gt;shen&lt;/em&gt; 深 (‘deep’), I felt &lt;em&gt;zhou&lt;/em&gt; 晝 (‘daylight’) also needed to be connected to &lt;em&gt;yong&lt;/em&gt; 慵 (‘laziness’) though a word such as ‘yet’ or ‘but’. Having extracted all the meaning we possibly can from the second line, we are set up for a beautiful conclusion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Cang&lt;/em&gt; 蒼 is a shade of deep green, and refers to &lt;em&gt;tai&lt;/em&gt; 苔 (‘moss’, also featured in &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/poets/wang-wei/deer-place&quot;&gt;Deer Place&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;. But Wang Wei doesn’t stop there. After these two characters he also adds the character &lt;em&gt;se&lt;/em&gt; 色, which means colour. This makes the colour of the moss, rather than the moss itself, the subject of this line. Some translators might use a literal word such as ‘colour’ here. But what is the poet &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; writing about? In a poem where each character conveys multiple meanings, here we have two characters intentionally emphasising one concept: the colour of the moss. I have chosen to use the ‘greenness’ of the green moss to playfully double up in the same way that the characters do, while also emphasising what I believe the poet imagined: a colour so vivid, a hue that permeated him so deeply, that he felt like the moss was climbing his robe.&lt;/p&gt;

          </description>
          <pubDate>Sat, 04 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
          <link>http://localhost:4000/poets/wang-wei/writing-on-a-happening</link>
          <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/poets/wang-wei/writing-on-a-happening</guid>
          
          
          <category>poets</category>
          
          <category>wang-wei</category>
          
        </item>
      
    
      
        <item>
          
            <title>Spring Dawn</title>
          
          <author> (Chinese Poetry)</author>
          <description>
            &lt;p&gt;This poem by Meng Haoran takes place after a sleepless night, and may have once been the most famous poem in China&lt;!--more--&gt;. It was one of the first poems that generations of educated Chinese children would memorise owing to its place on the first page of the anthology &lt;em&gt;Qianjia Shi&lt;/em&gt; 千家詩 (A Thousand Family Poems). Evidenced by many of his other poems, Meng Haoran liked to drink. Rather than reading this as a children’s poem, I like to imagine him with a hangover.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;春曉‌&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;春眠不覺曉，&lt;br /&gt;
處處聞啼鳥。&lt;br /&gt;
夜來風雨聲，&lt;br /&gt;
花落知多少。&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Spring Dawn&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Springtime, half-asleep, unaware of daybreak, &lt;br /&gt;
All around I hear birdsong. &lt;br /&gt;
Night brought noise, wind and rain, &lt;br /&gt;
Blossoms fell, who knows how many? &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;translation-notes&quot;&gt;Translation notes&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although the characters are quite easy to understand in this poem, a translation isn’t quite so straightforward.  It’s a challenge to translate each character in an order that is faithful to the original. Imagining the poet half-awake and articulating one thought after another helped me retain as much of the original structure as possible. I have attempted to create this effect by adding in punctuation to ensure that, similar to Chinese characters, each thought is self-contained. The only major deviation from the original word order is &lt;em&gt;sheng&lt;/em&gt; 聲 (‘noise’), which has moved from its original position at the end of the third line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A tool many translators use to get around this word order problem is to introduce a subject to most lines such as ‘I’ (for example, the first line would read as something like ‘In springtime &lt;em&gt;I am half-asleep&lt;/em&gt;, unaware of daybreak’). I have tried to avoid this work-around, because it provides the reader with extra assumptions, or noise, not present in the original.&lt;/p&gt;

          </description>
          <pubDate>Tue, 31 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
          <link>http://localhost:4000/poets/meng-haoran/spring-dawn</link>
          <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/poets/meng-haoran/spring-dawn</guid>
          
          
          <category>poets</category>
          
          <category>meng-haoran</category>
          
        </item>
      
    
      
        <item>
          
            <title>Behold The Deep Blue Sea</title>
          
          <author> (Chinese Poetry)</author>
          <description>
            &lt;p&gt;This poem by the warlord and statesman Cao Cao is one of the earliest examples of landscape poetry in Chinese recorded history&lt;!--more--&gt;. The genre of &lt;em&gt;shanshui&lt;/em&gt; 山水 (landscape, literally ‘mountain water’) poetry and art is what first drew me to Chinese history and culture. Almost two thousand years ago, between his numerous campaigns to unify Northern China and conquer neighbouring warlords, Cao Cao wrote the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;觀滄海&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;東臨碣石，以觀滄海。 &lt;br /&gt;
水何澹澹，山島竦峙。 &lt;br /&gt;
樹木叢生，百草豐茂。 &lt;br /&gt;
秋風蕭瑟，洪波湧起。 &lt;br /&gt;
日月之行，若出其中； &lt;br /&gt;
星漢燦爛，若出其里。 &lt;br /&gt;
幸甚至哉，歌以詠志。 &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Behold The Deep Blue Sea&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I headed east for Jieshi mountain, to behold the deep blue sea. &lt;br /&gt;
How rough and roiling the tide! Mountainous islands stand tall. &lt;br /&gt;
Thickets of trees thriving with life, a hundred plants flourish in bloom. &lt;br /&gt;
Autumn winds rustle and howl, vast waves gush forth. &lt;br /&gt;
The path of the sun and moon, as if emerging from the middle of it; &lt;br /&gt;
Stars shine and sparkle resplendent, as if born from within it. &lt;br /&gt;
Such a great fortune to behold! Let these words become a poem of remembrance. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;translation-notes&quot;&gt;Translation notes&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another poem with a title that immediately poses an imponderable question to a Western reader: what is the colour of the sea? &lt;em&gt;Cang&lt;/em&gt; 滄 is really the colour of the sea, somewhere between grey and blue. Here, I have chosen ‘deep blue’ to add depth to the colour, and the sea itself. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other tricky word in the title is &lt;em&gt;guan&lt;/em&gt; 觀 (to watch). This was also in the title of the previous poem, ‘Contemplating a Game of &lt;em&gt;Weiqi&lt;/em&gt;’. In that poem, Su Shi was listening to a game of &lt;em&gt;weiqi&lt;/em&gt; and writing a poem based on what he &lt;em&gt;imagined&lt;/em&gt;. So, translating the word as watching instead of contemplating would have been inaccurate. Here, Cao Cao is also not simply watching something. He headed east to &lt;em&gt;Jieshi&lt;/em&gt; mountain ‘in order to’ (a rough translation of &lt;em&gt;yi&lt;/em&gt; 以) watch the sea. So, he’s watching the sea from a vantage point, and contemplating the origin of the sun, moon and stars. Sounds more like ‘beholding’ to me. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remember, Cao Cao was a warlord. Many translations of this poem focus on some peace found within nature. Rather, I read his respect for the ferocity and power of nature. Where there are ambiguous characters such as &lt;em&gt;dan&lt;/em&gt; 澹 (tranquil, but can also be translated as rough when referring to the sea), I have elected to represent the full force of the scene.&lt;/p&gt;

          </description>
          <pubDate>Sat, 21 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
          <link>http://localhost:4000/poets/cao-cao/behold-the-deep-blue-sea</link>
          <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/poets/cao-cao/behold-the-deep-blue-sea</guid>
          
          
          <category>poets</category>
          
          <category>cao-cao</category>
          
        </item>
      
    
      
        <item>
          
            <title>Contemplating A Game Of Weiqi</title>
          
          <author> (Chinese Poetry)</author>
          <description>
            &lt;p&gt;Su Shi, one of the most accomplished figures in classical Chinese literature, takes us on a journey to watch white cranes and overhears a game of &lt;em&gt;weiqi&lt;/em&gt;&lt;!--more--&gt; - the Chinese name for the ancient board game Go. One of my favourite couplets comes at the end of this poem, a vivid imagining of living the good life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;觀棋&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;予素不解棋，嘗獨游廬山白鶴觀，觀中人皆闔戶晝寢，獨聞棋聲於古松流水之間，意欣然喜之，自爾欲學，然終不解也。兒子過乃粗能者，儋守張中日從之戲，予亦隅坐，竟日不以為厭也。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;五老峰前，白鶴遺址。&lt;br /&gt;
長松蔭庭，風日清美。&lt;br /&gt;
我時獨游，不逢一士。&lt;br /&gt;
誰歟棋者，戶外屨二。&lt;br /&gt;
不聞人聲，時聞落子。&lt;br /&gt;
紋枰坐對，誰究此味。&lt;br /&gt;
空鈎意釣，豈在魴鯉。&lt;br /&gt;
小兒近道，剝啄信指。&lt;br /&gt;
勝固欣然，敗亦可喜。&lt;br /&gt;
優哉游哉，聊復爾耳。&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contemplating A Game of Weiqi&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;    &lt;br /&gt;
I’m a simple person and don’t understand the game of &lt;em&gt;weiqi&lt;/em&gt;. I once travelled alone to the Lu mountains to see white cranes. Everyone who goes to watch the cranes tends to nap during the day behind closed doors. I could only hear the sound of &lt;em&gt;weiqi&lt;/em&gt; stones amid the old pine trees and flowing water. I rejoiced at the thought and took delight in it. That which I wanted to learn, I never ultimately understood.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;After my son passed away I made an effort to learn &lt;em&gt;weiqi&lt;/em&gt;, in order to take the responsibility to preserve a game followed by many in the Middle Kingdom and Japan. I found a nook to sit in, but the whole day I didn’t find any satisfaction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In front of &lt;em&gt;Wulao&lt;/em&gt; peak, a place vacated by white cranes. &lt;br /&gt;
Tall pines shade the courtyard, beautiful sunlight and a cool breeze. &lt;br /&gt;
When I was travelling alone, I didn’t meet a soul. &lt;br /&gt;
But who are these players? By the door two straw sandals. &lt;br /&gt;
No voice to be heard, the occasional sound of falling stones. &lt;br /&gt;
Sat opposite the patterned board, who can comprehend the essence of this scene? &lt;br /&gt;
When fishing with an empty hook, does one really expect to land bream and carp? &lt;br /&gt;
A small boy is close to the Way of things, as stones tap the board he trusts his fingers. &lt;br /&gt;
To win is certainly pleasurable, even defeat can be joyful. &lt;br /&gt;
Drifting along unhurried and easy! For a while like this and nothing more. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;translation-notes&quot;&gt;Translation notes&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a few tricky phrases, particularly in the preamble. It took me a while to figure out that &lt;em&gt;guo&lt;/em&gt; 过 (to pass) in this context might be a euphemism for his son passing away, much like the English usage of the word. Another tricky phrase is &lt;em&gt;bozhuo&lt;/em&gt; 剝啄 (purely onomatopoeic, used to convey a pecking sound or in modern usage the sound of tapping a window). I couldn’t come up with an English equivalent, so I had to insert the subject/object, ‘stones tap the board’. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The real action comes in the last line, with two phrases so famous that they have both entered the dictionary. However, as their usage has become more common, the dictionary definition doesn’t quite do justice to their poetic impact. The character &lt;em&gt;zai&lt;/em&gt; 哉 is an exclamation, and here we see it recur twice. So, a huge amount of emphasis is being placed here. Literally: Leisurely! Carefree! Finally, we have &lt;em&gt;liao&lt;/em&gt; 聊 (for a while) &lt;em&gt;fu&lt;/em&gt; 復 (a conjunction) &lt;em&gt;er&lt;/em&gt; 爾 (‘like this’ similar in meaning to &lt;em&gt;ran&lt;/em&gt; 然), and &lt;em&gt;er&lt;/em&gt; 耳 (&lt;em&gt;eryi&lt;/em&gt; 而已 in Modern Chinese, ‘and nothing else’).&lt;/p&gt;

          </description>
          <pubDate>Sun, 15 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
          <link>http://localhost:4000/poets/su-shi/contemplating-a-game-of-weiqi</link>
          <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/poets/su-shi/contemplating-a-game-of-weiqi</guid>
          
          
          <category>poets</category>
          
          <category>su-shi</category>
          
        </item>
      
    
      
        <item>
          
            <title>Deer Place</title>
          
          <author> (Chinese Poetry)</author>
          <description>
            &lt;p&gt;Let’s start from the beginning shall we? Not from the beginning of Chinese recorded history, rather my own experience with classical Chinese poetry&lt;!--more--&gt;. This was the first Chinese poem to really capture my attention. Much of Wang Wei’s writing is imbued with Buddhist themes. This poem is one of his most famous, and therefore one of his most translated. However, almost all translations focus only on the first stanza. The elusive second stanza hasn’t quite made it into popular culture, but I feel it adds much more meaning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;鹿柴&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;空山不見人，&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;但聞人語響。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;返景入深林，&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;復照青苔上。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;日夕見寒山，&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;便為獨往客。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;不知深林事，&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;但有麇麚跡。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Deer Place&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the wild mountain I see no people&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;but hear echoes of human voices&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;light returning enters the deep forest&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;once more illuminating green moss above&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In evening glow I watch the cold mountain&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;at the moment a lone traveller appears&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t know the ways of the deep forest&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;only the tracks left by the water deer&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;translation-notes&quot;&gt;Translation Notes&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first characters presented to us pose some fun challenges. First, the title, &lt;em&gt;Luzhai&lt;/em&gt; 鹿柴, is understood to be the name of a place close to where the poet lived. The second character is often translated as enclosure, or the title is often translated as &lt;em&gt;Deer Park&lt;/em&gt; but I have chosen to convey the meaning of a place where deer are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first characters of the poem itself &lt;em&gt;kongshan&lt;/em&gt; 空山 literally mean ‘empty mountain’. We can already get quite deep here, and try to reflect the poet’s focus on emptiness rather than the mountain itself. However, to Western eyes I think the idea of wilderness is more easily conveyed. A place where the poet is alone, which may already imply more spiritual ideas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first stanza is a joy to translate, so much so that &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.rochester.edu/College/translation/threepercent/2017/02/28/nineteen-ways-of-looking-at-wang-wei/&quot;&gt;an entire book&lt;/a&gt; has been written about the different approaches that can be taken. The poem can be read as taking place between two realms: the human realm which manifests itself more clearly as the poem goes on, and the spiritual realm represented by the elusive deer and depictions of the natural world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.learnancientchinesepoetry.org/2016/10/22/wang-wei-deer-park/&quot;&gt;Some translators&lt;/a&gt; take this idea further in the first stanza, by interpreting the character &lt;em&gt;fan&lt;/em&gt; 返 as referring to an indirect light source. Therefore, rather than the light returning after a period of absence, the light itself is being reflected from another object not mentioned (we might imagine from the leaves of a tree) and this &lt;em&gt;indirect&lt;/em&gt; light source illuminates the green moss. This dual meaning is tough to translate in poetic form, but the phrase ‘light returning’ is suitable because the light has something modifying it with this phrasing.&lt;/p&gt;

          </description>
          <pubDate>Mon, 09 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
          <link>http://localhost:4000/poets/wang-wei/deer-place</link>
          <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/poets/wang-wei/deer-place</guid>
          
          
          <category>poets</category>
          
          <category>wang-wei</category>
          
        </item>
      
    
  </channel>
</rss>
